Preliminary Guide to the Ruth Helm Osborn papers, 1956-2005 MS2278.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ruth Helm Osborn papers
1956-2005
1963-1980
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Osborn, Ruth Helm
MS2278.UA
14 Linear Feet
This collection contains photographs, slides, scrapbooks, articles, audio cassettes, and correspondence related to the work and life of Dr. Ruth Osborn. Dr. Osborn founded and directed the women's continuing education program at GW titled "Developing New Horizons for Women" from 1964 until her retirement in 1979.
Biographical / Historical
In 1964, Dr. Ruth Osborn (February 17, 1919 - October 30, 2009) created "Developing New Horizons for Women" a program that became the prototype for women's education programs in the 1960s and 1970s. The GW College of General Studies began the New Horizons for Women in 1964 with a noncredit orientation class of twenty women. "The purpose of the workshop, referred to as 'developing new horizons for women,' is to assist women to develop their potential: by enabling them to understand themselves as individuals and as women by exploring educational, occupational, and community service opportunities; and by analyzing and solving problems encountered when entering the educational and occupational world." (Operation Update, National Business Woman, October 1965). The focus of the GW program was mature married woman students many of whom had bachelors degrees, but had stopped their education and career following their marriages. She directed the GW Continuing Education Center for Women from 1964-1979 and focused her career on making education accessible for married women. Dr. Osborn was an active member of the organization Columbian Women. She received her B.S. from the University of Minnesota and an M.A. and Ed.D from GW. She retired in 1979. In 1998, GW honored Dr. Osborn with a distinguished alumni award.
Arrangement
Organized into 5 series: Scrapbooks, Personal papers, CEW records, Articles, and Columbian Women Scholarship Fund.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains reports, photographs, articles, brochures, slides, and scrapbooks. The scrapbooks contain photographs, correspondence, newspaper and magazines articles about Dr. Ruth Osborn and GW's Continuing Education for Women Program. These materials date from 1963-2005. Some of this material relates to the Columbian Women organization. These materials arrived in several donations from Ruth Osborn and have been divided into series related to both her work as an educator of women and the Continuing Education for Women program that she founded at GW.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ruth Osborn, 2009 [2009.068]. This collection also consists of previous donations by Ruth Osborn to the University Archives in 1999 and 2008.
Other Finding Aids
Those interested in researching the Columbian Women will find useful http://library.gwu.edu/ead/rg0027.xml
Continuing Education for Women Program; Women's rights; Washington (D.C.); Women's studies; Women -- History
- Scrapbooks, 1963-1996; 1963-1980; Series 1; Osborn, Ruth Helm; George Washington University. Division of Continuing Education; 4 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains scrapbooks that date from 1963-1996. The scrapbooks include photographs, correspondence, newspaper and magazines articles about Dr. Ruth Osborn and GW's Continuing Education for Women Program. Some of this material relates to the Columbian Women organization.
  This material was donated by Ruth Osborn from 1999-2008.
  Formerly ACC#737
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically. Some of the earlier scrapbooks arrived in a later accession and thus the box numbers are out of order and some of the scrapbooks overlap in date.
  Continuing Education for Women Program; Scrapbooks; Columbian Women, George Washington University, Washington (D.C.)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [1/3], 1963-1967; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [2/3], 1963-1967; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [3/3], 1963-1967; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Developing New Horizons for Women GWU scrapbook [1/4], 1964-1979; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Developing New Horizons for Women GWU scrapbook [2/4], 1964-1979; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Developing New Horizons for Women GWU scrapbook [3/4], 1964-1979; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Developing New Horizons for Women GWU scrapbook [4/4], 1964-1979; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook, 1964-1968; Series 1 (Flat box 12, Scrapbook 1)
  - Scrapbook [1/3], 1965-1972; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook [2/3], 1965-1972; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook [3/3], 1965-1972; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook [1/2], 1967-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook [2/2], 1967-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook [1/3], 1968-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook [2/3], 1968-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook [3/3], 1968-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook, 1969-1970; Series 1 (Flat box 12, Scrapbook 2)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [1/3], 1968-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [2/3], 1968-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [3/3], 1968-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [1/3], 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [2/3], 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [3/3], 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook [1/3], 1973-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook [2/3], 1973-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook [3/3], 1973-1979; Series 1 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [1/3], 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [2/3], 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [3/3], 1973-1974; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [1/3], 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [2/3], 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [3/3], 1975-1976; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [1/3], 1977-1980; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [2/3], 1977-1980; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Continuing Education for Women scrapbook [3/3], 1977-1980; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - loose scrapbook pages, undated; Series 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Personal papers, 1966-2005; 1966-1979; Series 2; 4 Linear Feet
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains biographical data related to Dr. Ruth Osborn including awards, correspondence, interviews, articles, and audio cassettes. These records date from 1966-2005. Most of the material relates to Dr. Osborn's work as an educator of women and a champion of the efforts of married women to combined careers with raising families.
  - Amici (friends), undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Anthropology, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Assistance to other colleges and Univ., 1970-1978; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    This file contains correspondence sent to Dr. Osborn regarding her assistance to other colleges and universities in setting up continuing education programs for women.
  - Assistance to U.S. Government Agencies, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 38)
  - Awards presented to Ruth Osborn, 1975-2005; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Awards presented to Ruth Osborn, 1975-1998; Series 2 (Flat box 12, Folder 1)
    This folder contains awards that were too big to fit in the folder titled Awards presented to Ruth Osborn housed in box 8.
  - Beta chapter nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn for the Phi Delta Gamma National Achievement Award, 1971 December; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Biographical and retirement data, 1968-1998, n.d.; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Biographical data, undated; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Compliments, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 35)
  - Compliments, undated; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Copyright, undated; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, personal, undated; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Creativity workbook creative thinking and problem solving by James M. Osborn, 1974-1975; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Credit programs, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Diplomas, undated; Series 2 (Flat box 12, Folder 2)
  - Economics, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Equal Rights /Women's Rights, undated; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - History, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Honors for Ruth Osborn, Circa 1960s; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Honors: RHO AAUW, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Honors: other GWU awards, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Honoring RHO and Hibbing Jr. College, 1992; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 26)
  - Interview [morton] Osborn and Ruth Helm Osborn, 1977; Series 2 (Box 13, Cassette 7)
    This is an audiocassette
  - Loose papers [1/2], 1970s-1990s; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    The material in this folder relates to the Columbian Women organization. The order in which the loose documents were found in the box was maintained.
  - Loose papers [2/2], 1970s-1990s; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    The material in this folder relates to the Columbian Women organization. The order in which the loose documents were found in the box was maintained. The folder shows Osborn's involvement with this organization.
  - Loose papers, 1971-1974; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Loose papers, undated; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Loose papers, undated; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Manual, 1975; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    General
    A counselor's guide for the Workbook Developing New Horizons for Women Career Development for Employed Women by Ruth Osborn, Marjorie M. Parks, Abbie O. Smith, and Helen O. Wolle
  - Middle States Evaluation, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Motimation, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Notebook of programs throughout the United States [1/2], 1966-1978; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Notebook of programs throughout the United States [2/2], 1966-1978; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Osborn, RHO, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Other reports, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Papers, 1970; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    This folder is titles as it was originally and the papers in the folder remain in the order and in the folder as they were donated. The folder contains correspondence and articles.
  - Papers, 1971; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Papers, 1972; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Papers, 1979; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Physiology, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Professional Women, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - RHO file, undated; Series 2 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - RHO: honors GWU distinguished alumni achievement award, 1998; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - RHO and ML Kerr American Women, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - RHO: resume, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 29)
  - RHO: University of Minnesota outstanding educator award, 2005; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 24)
  - RHO: University of Minnesota honors, 2005; Series 2 (Box 18, Floppy disk 23)
  - Ruth Osborn file, undated; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Special Fellowship for Women M. Parks, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 34)
  - Speeches - RHO, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 36)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: National newspapers, magazines, periodical articles, 1956-1978; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: articles and research reports, 1964-1969; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    The material in this file came from a folder with this label, but no information about what the nomination this material supports.
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn Radio and television programs national and local, 1964-1977; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: Speaking engagements to other colleges and national organizations, 1967-1982; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: Newspaper articles, 1969-1975; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: Honors to Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn, 1968-1984; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: CEW brochures and newsletters, 1968, undated; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: CEW newsletters, 1968-1975; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: Developing New Horizons for Women, 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: Retirement from GW, 1979; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: Additional information, 1969-2002; Series 2 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Support information for nomination of Dr. Ruth Helm Osborn: Speeches to organizations in Metropolitan Washington DC area, undated; Series 2 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Teacher Aids, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 37)
  - Trophy, 1929; Series 2 (Box 17, Item 1)
    Hibbing Home Play Essay Contest 1929 5th Grade Champion
  - Women on Government, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 28)
  - Women's Studies, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Women's Studies, undated; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - Zonta Dinner, 06/24/1974; Series 2 (Box 13, Cassette 10)
    On tape label: "Hezvi Sippilla"
  - Zonta Int. Conv. with Harriette Yeckel, 06/23/1974; Series 2 (Box 13, Cassette 11)
  - Zonta Int. Conv. status of women, 06/30/1974; Series 2 (Box 13, Cassette 12)
  - 1st Day Zonta, 06/27/1974??; Series 2 (Box 13, Cassette 13)
  - Zonta records, undated; Series 2 (Flat box 12, Folder 3)
- CEW records, 1964-1997; 1964-1975; Series 3; 5 Linear Feet
  This series contains records of the Continuing Education for Women Program called Developing New Horizons through Continuing Education. This program was founded by Dr. Ruth Osborn in 1964. Dr. Osborn "developed the program as the result of her own experience as a mature woman returning to colleage to work on her doctorate. On the George Washington campus, she saw other women like herself seeking new ways to employ their abilities.... Dr. Osborn decided that the first need of a returning woman student was encouragement, a restored confidence in her ability to study and work.... During 15 two-hour sessions... the women gather for lectures and discussions. They hear guest speakers who come to discuss career fields open to women." (Women Moving Ahead by Alice Y. Scates, Ameircan Education March, 1966).
  These records include correspondence, audio recordings of CEW events, course related materials such as schedules and course descriptions, a handbook, and slides. These records date from 1964-1997.
  Box 1 is unprocessed and the three folders (with original folder titles) have been added to the end of this series.
  - Brochures and press releases, 1971-1972; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - CEW event Tape 1, 06/04/1975; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 1)
    On tape label: "panel speakers, Marvin Th. both sides complete"
  - CEW event Tape 2, 06/04/1975; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 2)
    On tape label: "panel speakers, Marvin Theater. both sides complete"
  - CEW event Tape 3, 06/04/1975; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 3)
    On tape label: "Side 1: am panel; 15 min. only. side 2 complete after lunch speakers"
  - CEW event Tape 4, 06/04/1975; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 3)
    On tape label: Bess Myerson side 1 only" Side 2 is blank
  - Co-education, undated; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Continuing education for women, 1967-1979; Series 3 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1979; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: letters from students [1/2], undated; Series 3 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: letters from students [2/2], undated; Series 3 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Course related documents, 1960-1997; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Course rosters New Horizons [1/2], 1964-1972; Series 3 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Course rosters New Horizons [2/2], 1965-1972; Series 3 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Cultural blocks to women's education, undated; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Development and Administration of Continuing Education for Women, 1964-1974; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General note
    This folder is not processed and has been added to Series 3 at the bottom. The folder title is original as are the order of the three folders in box 1.
  - A handbook for administrators of continuing education for women programs, 1977; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - History, 1962-1970s; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - International visitors, undated; Series 3 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Interviews and lectures, Circa 1960s; Series 3 (Box 14)
    This boxes is composed of reel-to-reel audio recordings primarily of interviews and lectures from CEW courses.
  - Interviews and lectures, Circa 1960s; Series 3 (Box 15)
  - Interviews and lectures, Circa 1960s; Series 3 (Box 17)
  - Model Prog for Est. or Expanding Counseling Program for Women, 1978; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 8)
  - NH women at Col. Women, 10/18/1975; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 5)
  - Binder - photos, undated; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Philosophy, undated; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Publicity CEW, undated; Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Reports CEW, Series 2 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Slides of courses [1/2], 1974-1978; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Slides of courses [2/2], 1974-1978; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Slides of courses, 1976-1977; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Sociology, Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Symposium Dr. Osborn Margaret Bruce Robins Murry, [Bani] Hah, 1974; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 9)
  - Wst panel on IWY, 10/16/1975; Series 3 (Box 13, Cassette 6)
  - Women's Studies, undated; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Women Studies, undated; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Women Studies binder, undated; Series 3 (Box 17, Folder data_value_missing_a099411a2a1e86243ff6238019439d8d)
- Articles, 1959-1992; Series 4; 1 Linear Feet
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains articles about the Continuting Education Program for Women and also articles more generally about women, education and labor. These materials date from 1959-1992.
  - Articles, 1959-1979, n.d.; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Articles, 1973; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 33)
  - Articles, 1975; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - Articles, 1976; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - Background research articles [1/2], 1964-1975; Series 4 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Background research articles [1/2], 1975-1992, n.d.; Series 4 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - CEW RHO's articles, undated; Series 4 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - "No More Crumbs' introduction, undated; Series 4 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Published articles GWU alumni review 1963, Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - RHO: publications, undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - RHO: publications "adult leadership", undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - RHO publication "adult leadership", 1975; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - RHO publication "GWU Club Woman", undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Publications "retired officer", undated; Series 4 (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Written by Ruth Osborn: articles and research papers, 1971-1981, n.d.; Series 4 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Columbian Women Scholarship Fund, 1957-1996; 1960-1989; Series 5; 0.05 Linear Feet
  This series contains meeting minutes, directories, and other records related to the Columbian Women organization. The Columbian Women, the University's oldest scholarship support group was founded in 1894. These records date from 1957-1996 and come from Ruth Osborn's personal files related to her time with the organization.
  This series is not fully processed and may require more time to use for research.
  - Columbian Women meeting minutes, 1974-1977; Series 5 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Women, 1979-1981; Series 5 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Columbian Women Historians responsibilities and reports, 1957-1975; Series 5 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Columbian Women directories, 1960-1971; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Columbian Women directories, 1971-1989, 1996; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 2)